We've done opposite API, at least the core functionality of what most people are using it for.
And now, it's time to hop on over to the bridge to composition API.
But again, the key thing here is the bridge, because we're not going to go fully into it yet,
we're going to see kind of the intermediary and sort of learn the progression from options to composition.
All right. So, let's take a look at our code.
Let me go open up restaurant page.
Okay.
So, we've learned that when it comes to integrating types with object API or options API,
we can see here we had to do like define component, we had to do some, you know, things to pass it into like the data to kind of make it look right.
And then, especially when it came to props, we had prop types of, wouldn't it be nice things are just a little bit easier, a little bit more native?
Right? What if we want it more standard JavaScript, less of the guardrails that options API provides for us?
And that's really where composition API comes into play.
And so, the one thing I have to underscore actually a lot right now, which I forgot to animate to, is that the composition API does not replace the options API.
Contrary to a lot, I know people love like buzzwords and things going viral, and I think there was a blog post where I think someone was claiming it at one point.
So, that message had become kind of like pervaded throughout, unfortunately.
And the options API actually believe it or not is something that we can very easily support as the view team, because underlying what we've written,
options API is basically one style of writing components.
So, when people are like, oh, this is going to go away, it's just a style of writing components.
There's nothing unique about what's going on there, because the composition API and the options API are powered by the same like core library.
So, I just need that to be just, just keep pushing that message, so people don't feel like, oh, no, my options API is going away.
No, it's not, but there is another way to help us solve other problems, which we'll see in a little bit.
Alright, so taking a look at this, let's start to see what composition API might look like.
So, one of the things I mentioned with composition API is that it does things a little bit more like vanilla JavaScript.
So, for example, here with data, we have this function that's returning in object, and then we have computer properties, we have all these guard rails.
Let's take a look at what it might look like inside of composition API instead.
And so, the way that you know your inside composition API is through the setup lifecycle hook.
So, for those who come from view two, you might be familiar with like on like mounted, created all those lifecycle hooks.
Setup is the first one that runs at the beginning now of all the component lifecycle methods.
And so, what we're going to do is we're just going to migrate our options API stuff into composition API, just to show you where that progression is, so that then later when we take that next jump, it won't be so drawing.
So, first thing first, we're going to start by setting up our reactive data.
And so, remember what I said inside of composition API is that everything inside of here is vanilla JavaScript.
So, in other words, when you set up a constant of filter text, that is literally what it is.
It is a constant of filter text. It's not going to change. It's not going to be reactive because this is vanilla JavaScript plan.
So, what do we need? We need to tell it that we need some help from view.
And so, the helper method that we're going to stick with for this particular workshop is going to be rough.
So, think of a reactive reference, that's what that is. So, we say, oh, this is going to be a rough that is an empty string.
This tells us that, okay, this is going to be the equivalent of this right here inside of our data.
So, that's been moved. Next, we're going to go ahead and let's move restaurant list.
So, show me someone to copy restaurant list over here.
And then I'm going to const this as well, const restaurant list equals a rough that's an array. So, this is a reactive array.
Not array. Yes, a reactive array. Okay.
Finally, we got to move our show new form here. So, I'm going to move that over here and const show new form.
And this is not going to be false, but this will be a rough of false, just like that.
And so, now that we've deleted all this, you'll notice now that we are in a sort of untype territory again.
Because when we look and hover over filter text, you'll see that now we have this new type that's being inherited called a rough.
This is a reactive reference. So, think of this, like when you were looking at options API and you had like data methods and all these specific types.
This is now saying that, okay, we know how to handle this specific type of rough, which is a reactive reference within view.
And so, here you'll see that restaurant list actually does say, oh, actually similarly, let me detect the shape of the objects I'm noticing inside of my array.
But we want to go ahead and say, hey, this is in array of restaurants. So, the way that we do this is with typecasting, just like we did before, where we say, ah, this should be a restaurant array.
And just like that, now we've gone ahead and actually define our rough correctly.
And so, this should start to feel a little bit more like a type script.
Okay, and then going forward here, we have here, we have a rough. This is a Boolean, so we're good on this end.
So, you'll notice though that none of it is actually showing up as being used, right, saying, oh, it's unused.
And that's because inside of the setup function, again, we're in vanilla JavaScript land, so we need to be a little bit more explicit.
And so, we need to actually manually return these specific variables, whereas data just assumed you're going to use them.
In the setup function, you might have some that are private variables, some that you want to expose.
So, we want you to be explicit in this particular format of setup when it comes to returning this stuff.
So, once again, I can return this, show new form, and now that I have this, everything is now, you can feed into the options API, just like you normally would.
But again, we're learning more about composition API, so let's continue this journey and migrate everything over.
So, for computer properties now, we have these reactive references, we have a computer helper method, and this is the computer helper method, it's just like the ref.
Where we're basically saying, this is going to be a computer property that's based on view.
So, here, let's go ahead and grab this, let's start with number of restaurants, that's the easiest one.
So, number of restaurants here is going to be a computer property, so this is the helper computed, and it's going to be a function that returns a reactive variable.
Now, what you'll first notice though is that it's going to yell at us, because it's, hey, wait a second, where does filtered restaurant lists exist?
Well, it doesn't, because this is not working anymore, we're in vanilla JavaScript land, this is not automatically taking care for us by options API.
But what we do have, we do have this, oh wait, what am I talking about?
That is because filter restaurant list is here, and then I'll show you what I'm talking about in a second.
Okay, so I can do const equals computed, and then this is a function that returns this stuff.
Now, once again, we're still in a similar problem though, because as we notice, this does not exist, therefore it can't find this restaurant list property.
But we know restaurant list does exist right here, and so your first thought might be, well, in JavaScript land, so easy, I'm going to go ahead and just delete this, it should work.
It does not work, the reason for that is because reactive references play on basically an object definition syntax for tracking reactivity and proxies, which we're not going to get into.
So basically, when you're using composition API with reactive references, particularly the ref helper, you need to unpack the value, because otherwise it's just a constant you're working with, this is why there's no filter.
And so if we add this dot value to our reactive reference, you notice that something everything opens up.
It knows what the restaurant is, it knows what to grab, and so whenever using ref basically remember that you have this dot value that you need to unpack.
And so for those who are new to composition API though, you might be thinking, oh, that's kind of weird, I don't know if I like that, because in options API, it just worked, right, this dot, restaurant list, go to go.
The thing about it is though, because you're in sort of an illegitimate land, one of the benefits that the dot value actually affords you is that it does make it very explicit to developers that you're working with a reactive reference.
So if you use the reactive helper method, which I'll just show you real quick.
So if we say like cons to do item equals reactive, so this is another helper method, where it might be like ID123, although actually let me just show you the text page tree, just as a reminder, we can use that and just scaffold that and then like title, get milk, right.
The reactive object does allow you to just go to do item dot title, and then it just works.
But if this were a ref, you do need to do value dot title. And so some people go, oh, well then I, I'm just going to use reactive, and that's totally up to you.
Again, I've seen people go both ways on this, it depends on you and your team.
I'm using ref just because I think that's the one that tends to catch people off guard when they're not used to using it.
So I want people just get a little bit more exposure and so that when you see it and you're working with it, you're not confused.
If you want to just,